<metadata xml:lang="en"><idinfo><native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3000</native><descript><abstract>Ecological regions denote areas of general similarity in ecosystems and in the type, quality, and quantity of environmental resources. They are designed to serve as a spatial framework for the research, assessment, management, and monitoring of ecosystems and ecosystem components. These general purpose regions are critical for structuring and implementing ecosystem management strategies across international, national, province and state agencies, and nongovernment organizations that are responsible for different types of resources within the same geographical areas.

A Roman numeral hierarchical scheme has been adopted for different levels for ecological regions. Level I is the coarsest level, dividing North America into 15 ecological regions. Level II divides the continent into 50 regions. At Level III, there are currently 181 ecological regions for North America.

These files of Level I ecological regions of North America are a 2010 update and revision of files developed by Canada, the United States, and Mexico in  2006, which were an update of earlier files from the late 1990's in a cooperative project for the Commission for Environmental Cooperation (CEC 1997). The CEC was created under the North American Agreement on Environmental Cooperation (NAAEC) to address regional environmental concerns, help prevent potential trade and environmental conflicts and promote the effective enforcement of environmental law. The Agreement complements the environmental provisions established in the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA).

The 2006 version of North American ecological regions was developed in a meeting between representatives of the three nations in April 2006 in Newport, Oregon. This 2010 version updates mainly the United States ecoregions in those states where new ecoregion mapping has occurred since 2006, particularly in Michigan, New York, and New England. Issues relating to topology (overlaps and gaps in the data) and to waterbodies were the only revisions for Canada and Mexico. Many small waterbodies in Mexico and in coastal areas of the United States were merged with surrounding ecoregions to conform with their depiction in the interior United States and Canada. The 2010 files are considered draft and subject to further refinements.Commission for Environmental Cooperation. 1997. Ecological regions of North America: toward a common perspective. Commission for Environmental Cooperation, Montreal, Quebec, Canada. 71pp.

 U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, 2010, Level III ecoregions of the continental United States (revision of Omernik, 1987): Corvallis, Oregon, USEPA National Health and Environmental Effects Research Laboratory, Map M-1, various scales.

Comments and questions regarding the North America Ecoregions should be addressed to Glenn Griffith, USGS, c/o US EPA., 200 SW 35th Street, Corvallis, OR 97333, (541)-754-4465, email:griffith.glenn@epa.gov.  Alternate: James Omernik, USGS, c/o US EPA, 200 SW 35th Street, Corvallis, OR 97333, (541)-754-4458, email:omernik.james@epa.gov</abstract><purpose>Ecoregion maps assist managers of aquatic and terrestrial resources to understand the regional patterns of the realistically attainable quality of these resources</purpose><supplinf>Electronic versions of ecoregion maps and posters, as well as other ecoregion resources are available at: https://www.epa.gov/eco-research/ecoregions.
      Symbology layers for US Levels III and IV also available.
      Level IV ecoregions are not complete for California and Arizona, as of May, 2010.  For these states, the polygons are for Level III or lower. The field "US_L4CODE" contains placeholder information derived from "US_L3CODE".  Ecoregions were digitized at 1:250,000 scale and are intended for large geographic extents (i.e. states, multiple counties, or river basins).  Use for smaller areas, such as individual counties or a 1:24,000 scale map boundary, is not recommended.</supplinf></descript><citation><citeinfo><title>NA_Eco_Level1</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><origin>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</origin><pubinfo><publish>U.S. EPA Office of Research &amp; Development (ORD) - National Health and Environmental Effects Research Laboratory (NHEERL)</publish><pubplace>Corvallis, OR</pubplace></pubinfo><serinfo/><lworkcit><citeinfo><title/><pubdate/><pubinfo/><serinfo/></citeinfo></lworkcit><onlink>ftp://newftp.epa.gov/EPADataCommons/ORD/Ecoregions/cec_na/NA_CEC_Eco_Level1.zip</onlink><pubdate>20100501</pubdate><onlink>https://www.epa.gov/eco-research/ecoregions</onlink></citeinfo></citation><timeperd><current>Publication date</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20100501</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Ongoing</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-180.000000</westbc><eastbc>180.000000</eastbc><northbc>84.132635</northbc><southbc>6.630919</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Selected State, Conterminous United States</placekey></place><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>biota</themekey><themekey>boundaries</themekey><themekey>environment</themekey><themekey>location</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>EPA GIS Keyword Thesaurus</themekt><themekey>Biology</themekey><themekey>Conservation</themekey><themekey>Ecology</themekey><themekey>Ecosystem</themekey><themekey>Land</themekey><themekey>Natural Resources</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>United States</placekey></place><theme><themekt>User</themekt><themekey>US Ecoregion Levels III and IV, North American (CEC) Ecoregion Levels I, II, III</themekey></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><crossref><citeinfo><title>Ecoregions of the United States</title></citeinfo></crossref><secinfo><secsys>FIPS Pub 199</secsys><secclass>No Confidentiality</secclass><sechandl>Standard Technical Controls</sechandl></secinfo><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Research &amp; Development (ORD) - National Health and Environmental Effects Research Laboratory (NHEERL)</cntorg><cntper>Randy Comeleo</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Analyst</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>200 S.W. 35th St.</address><city>Corvallis</city><state>OR</state><postal>97333</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(541) 754-4491</cntvoice><cntemail>comeleo.randy@epa.gov</cntemail><cntinst>http://www.epa.gov/</cntinst></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataIdInfo><envirDesc>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3000</envirDesc><dataLang><languageCode value="en"/></dataLang><idCitation><resTitle>NA_Eco_Level1</resTitle><presForm><PresFormCd value="005"/></presForm></idCitation><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd value="001"/></spatRpType><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native"><westBL>-4334051.501</westBL><eastBL>3324076.2511</eastBL><northBL>4267264.5003</northBL><southBL>-3313739.25</southBL><exTypeCode>1</exTypeCode></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt><geoBox esriExtentType="decdegrees"><westBL>-180</westBL><eastBL>180</eastBL><northBL>84.132635</northBL><southBL>6.630919</southBL><exTypeCode>1</exTypeCode></geoBox></dataIdInfo><metainfo><metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><mettc>local time</mettc><metd>20101129</metd><metfrd>20140920</metfrd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>US EPA</cntorg><cntper>Randy Comeleo</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Analyst</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>200 S.W. 35th St</address><city>Corvallis</city><state>OR</state><postal>97333</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(541) 754-4491</cntvoice><cntemail>comeleo.randy@epa.gov</cntemail><cntinst>http://www.epa.gov/</cntinst></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><mdLang><languageCode value="en"/></mdLang><mdStanName>ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer>DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer><mdChar><CharSetCd value="004"/></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005"/></mdHrLv><mdHrLvName>dataset</mdHrLvName><distinfo><resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc><distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the Environmental Protection Agency, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. It is strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file</distliab><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Research &amp; Development (ORD) - National Health and Environmental Effects Research Laboratory (NHEERL)</cntorg><cntper>Randy Comeleo</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>GIS Analyst</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>200 S.W. 35th St.</address><city>Corvallis</city><state>OR</state><postal>97333</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(541) 754-4491</cntvoice><cntemail>comeleo.randy@epa.gov</cntemail><cntinst>http://www.epa.gov/</cntinst></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><orDesc>002</orDesc><linkage>file://\\DC2626XMWEBER\E$\Ecoregions\Updated_Ecoregions\Eco_Level_III_US.shp</linkage><protocol>Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc><transSize>44.168</transSize></distorTran><distorFormat><formatName>Shapefile</formatName></distorFormat></distributor></distInfo><mdDateSt>20101129</mdDateSt><dataqual><lineage><srcinfo><srccontr>The state borders were derived from the dtl_st.sdc on the ArcGIS DVD provided by ESRI.  It was modified by removing Alaska and Hawaii polygons and all but the State field, adding some coastal islands based on imagery or NHDPlus areas, and restoring topology (removing internal gaps and small overlaps).  The EPA regions were added to this custom geodatabase (dtl_48plyf) prior to the intersection process with the seamless ecoregion data.</srccontr></srcinfo><procstep><procdate>20100526</procdate><procdesc>1) U.S.G.S. 1:250,000 topographic maps are used to delineate the ecoregions. The lines drawn are manually digitized or scanned to produce georeferenced electronic files. 2) All base maps are joined together and errors along the edges are resolved. 3) Topology is established and the maps are reviewed for accuracy, completeness, and conformity with the original lines. Corrections are made as needed and topology regenerated. 4) Attributes are added. 5) Maps are plotted for visual inspection by two individuals and necessary changes made.  6) Ecoregions from all available states are merged and dissolved to identify and correct inconsistencies. 7) Polygons of the corrected seamless ecoregion features are extended beyond the coastal borders.  8) State and Ecoregion datasets are intersected. 9) Topology errors removed. 10) Final QA</procdesc></procstep></lineage><logic>Although ecoregion polygons and attributes have been checked for accuracy, some errors may remain.
    Polygons along state borders were reviewed and updated, May 2010.</logic><complete>Ecoregion development is ongoing in the United States and may be integrated into the North America data in the future.  This pertains mainly to the states of California and Arizona.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Data were collected using methods that have unknown accuracy (EPA National Geospatial Data Policy [NGDP] Accuracy Tier 10). For more information, please see EPA's NGDP at https://www.epa.gov/geospatial/epa-national-geospatial-data-policy)</horizpar></horizpa></posacc></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Vector</direct><ptvctinf><sdtsterm><sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype><ptvctcnt>2140</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><planci><plance>coordinate pair</plance><plandu>meters</plandu><coordrep><absres>0.000001</absres><ordres>0.000001</ordres></coordrep></planci><mapproj><mapprojn>Lambert Azimuthal Equal Area</mapprojn><lamberta><longpc>-100.000000</longpc><latprjc>45.000000</latprjc><feast>0.000000</feast><fnorth>0.000000</fnorth></lamberta></mapproj></planar><geodetic><horizdn>D_Sphere_ARC_INFO</horizdn><ellips>Sphere_ARC_INFO</ellips><semiaxis>6370997.000000</semiaxis><denflat>infinity</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode>Sphere_ARC_INFO_Lambert_Azimuthal_Equal_Area</identCode></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spatRepInfo><VectSpatRep><topLvl><TopoLevCd value="001"/></topLvl><geometObjs><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd value="001"/></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt>1605</geoObjCnt></geometObjs></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>NA_Eco_Level1</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>FID</attrlabl><attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>NA_L1CODE</attrlabl><attrdef>Code for Level I Ecoregion (North America)</attrdef><attrdefs>CEC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>NA_L1NAME</attrlabl><attrdef>Name for Level I Ecoregion (North America)</attrdef><attrdefs>CEC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>NA_L1KEY</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape_Leng</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape_Area</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr></detailed></eainfo></metadata>
